A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, President's Office, Richard W. Lyman papers FA1169
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, President's Office, Richard W. Lyman papers
1987-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Lyman, Richard W. (1923-2012)
FA1169
1.69 Cubic Feet 1 standard record storage box and 1 letter document box.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged materials are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in one series - Speeches and Remarks.
Related Materials
For Richard Lyman's personal papers, please see the Richard W. Lyman papers (FA1276).
Biographical / Historical
Richard W. Lyman was born in Philadelphia on October 18, 1923.
Lyman began his undergraduate studies at Swarthmore College in 1940, but his education was interrupted when he was drafted for military service in 1943. He served in the Army Air Forces Weather Service until 1946. He graduated from Swarthmore in 1947 and went on to complete both a master's degree and a Ph.D. in history at Harvard University.
While a doctoral student specializing in contemporary British history, he was named a Fulbright Fellow, an opportunity that allowed him to spend a year studying at the London School of Economics. He also spent his summers earning money by writing articles for The Economist.
Lyman went on to teach history at Harvard, Swarthmore, and Washington University in St. Louis. In 1958, just after the publication of his first book The First Labour Government, 1924, he accepted a position as an associate professor at Stanford University. By 1962 he had been promoted to full professor. Two years later Lyman was named Associate Dean of the School of Humanities and Sciences at Stanford, and he later served as University Provost. By 1970 he was appointed President of Stanford, a position he held for ten years, during which time he successfully increased the University's revenues and enrollment.
Lyman's tenure was also characterized by the political unrest and demands for change that affected many university campuses during this time. While he worked to diversify the student body and personally opposed the Vietnam War, as president he faced violent student protests and university sit-ins that disrupted the order of campus life. In 2009 he recounted these years in Stanford in Turmoil: Campus Unrest, 1966-1972.
Lyman was offered the presidency of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) in 1980 following the sudden death of John Knowles. Lyman had been a member of the RF Board of Trustees for four years and had also chaired its Commission on the Humanities. He took over the Foundation during a period of continuing evolution. He led initiatives in genetic engineering in agriculture, and he oversaw the mobilization of technology to support growth in the developing world. Closer to home, the Foundation looked for ways to combat poverty in America's inner cities, and RF support encouraged multimedia artists and emerging filmmakers.
Lyman retired from the RF in 1988 and returned to Stanford University in order to help establish the Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies. He served as the Institute's director until 1991. In recognition of Lyman's longstanding interest in the humanities and technology, in 2002 the RF allocated $500,000 to the National Humanities Center to create the Richard W. Lyman Award, which honored those who used information technology to advance the field of the humanities. This award was granted from 2002 to 2006.
Richard Lyman died of congestive heart failure in Palo Alto, California, on May 27, 2012. He was 88 years old.
Scope and Contents
Contains speeches and remarks prepared and given by Richard W. Lyman at various seminars, conferences and events, as well as Rockefeller Foundation Board meetings and celebrations during the period 1987-1988.
- Speeches and Remarks, 1987-1988; 1
  - Dinner Remarks, 1987 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - INTERPHIL Conference, Windsor Castle, Windsor, England, 1987 June 24-26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AGBUC Rebuttal (in response to H. Wasser Article), 1987 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stanford-Harvard Caper, Los Angeles, CA, 1987 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John W. Gardner Leadership Award, 75th Birthday Celebration, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Symposium on Evil, Salado, Texas, 1987 October 23-25 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - CHART - South Carolina, 1987 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Womens Way Conference, Philadelphia, PA, 1987 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Indiana University Talk, 1987 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Carnegie Corporation - "Strengthening Democratic Institutions", 1988 January 26-27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Society of Fundraising Executives meeting, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Welfare Reform Conference, 1988 February 16-18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - I.S. Research Forum - "The Future of the Non-Profit Sector", 1988 March 17-18 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - National University Continuing Education Association Conference (NUCEA), Philadelphia, PA, 1988 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Preface - Philanthropics - Voluntary Action, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Stanford University - Centennial Celebration, New York, 1988 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Center for the Study of Philanthropy - Reagan Among the Corinthians, 1988 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - World Congress on Philanthropy, 1988 May 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Institute of International Education (IIE) - Keynote Address, 1988 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rockefeller Foundation 75th Anniversary Celebration, 1988 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Seminar at the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, 1988 May 25-27 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Reception Honoring Richard W. Lyman, Harvard Club, 1988 June 2 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting - Remarks by Richard W. Lyman, 1988 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 27)